Guide to the Full Frame Archive Collection, 1998-2017 RL.00424
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- DoubleTake Film Festival, 2001
  - Amato: A Love Affair with Opera (2000)
    This uplifting film tells the story of the Tony and Sally Amato and the opera company they created in 1948 and have nurtured for over 50 years. They orchestrated every aspect of Amato Opera Company productions, in its tiny opera house in the Bowery: direction, training, costumes and even catering. In the process, they provided rare opportunities and support for young singers. Tony's almost manic energy, balanced by Sally's smiling calm and the powerful bond of love between them form the core of this tight-knit community-together, completely in love with opera.
    - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, TRT 57:00 (Box 5)
    - DVD master, TRT 57:00 (Box 4)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - Avant de Partir (2000)
    English title: Before Leaving
    Directed by: Marie de Laubier
    Produced by: Marie de Laubier
    Country: France
    An unsentimental portrayal of Mapi, a retirement home in the Paris suburbs, its director Dr. Yamina Abbes, and its elderly residents. The residents, who suffer from various psychoses, Alzheimer's and other forms of dementia, are cared for with patience and humor by Dr. Abbes and her staff, from entry through day-to-day life, to eventual death. The film reveals the personalities, fears, pains, joy and dignity of this small community.
    In French with English subtitles
    - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, TRT 91:00 (Box 5)
    - DVD master, TRT 91:00 (Box 4)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - Benjamin Smoke (2000)
    Directed by: Jem Cohen and Peter Sillen
    Produced by: Noah Cohen
    Filmed over ten years in 16mm, this is a character portrait of Benjamin (1960-1999, no last name), presented in a fragmentary collage of still and moving images, interviews, and rehearsal and performance footage. Lead singer/songwriter of the underground band Smoke, speed addict, sometime drag queen, rail-thin misfit, Benjamin speaks openly about his life, from his home in Cabbagetown, a poverty-stricken, marginal neighborhood in Atlanta, Georgia. The film concludes with a musical eulogy from Patti Smith.
    - Preservation print, 16mm, so., b/w, reel 1 of 4, 720 ft. (Box 9)
    - Preservation print, 16mm, so., b/w, reel 2 of 4, 720 ft. (Box 9)
    - Preservation print, 16mm, so., b/w, reel 3 of 4, 720 ft. (Box 9)
    - Preservation print, 16mm, so., b/w, reel 4 of 4, 720 ft. (Box 9)
    - DVD master, TRT 80:00 (Box 4)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - Shanti (2000)
    Directed by: Rohan Sen
    Produced by: Rohan Sen
    TRT: 7:20
    The pastoral peacefulness of people reposing on benches in a New York park is contrasted with the rowdy roar, frenzy and noises of the city that surrounds them. A beautiful meditation elegantly shot in black and white.
    - Preservation print, 16mm, so., b/w, reel 1 of 1, 264 ft. (Box 1)
    - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, TRT 7:20 (Box 1)
    - DVD master, TRT 7:20 (Box 4)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - Festival materials, 2001
    - Program Book, 2001 DoubleTake Film Festival (2001) (Box 6)
    - Programs and News Clippings, 2001 (Box 13)
    - Press Releases, 2001 (Box 13)
    - T-Shirt, 2001 (Box 13)
    - Tote Bag, 2001 (Box 13)
    - Baseball Hat, 2001 (Box 13)
    - Program, 2001 (Box 19)
    - Newspaper Ad, 2001 (Box 19)
- Full Frame Film Festival, 2002
  - The First Year (2001)
    Directed by: Davis Guggenheim
    Produced by: Davis Guggenheim and Julia Schachter
    Award won: Full Frame Grand Jury Award
    Five young teachers in Los Angeles public schools are followed through their first year of teaching in some of the U.S.'s toughest elementary, middle and high schools. Maurice Rabb, Nate Monley, Geneviève DeBose, Joy Kraft-Watts, and Georgene Acosta struggle to keep their students in school, fight city hall for funding, find special services, even teach without a classroom. The First Year shows what happens when the system fails to serve, when families fail to support, and what the teachers must do when their idealism isn't enough, cutting through the rhetoric of the national debate about education to remind us of the powerful relationship between a teacher and a student.
    In English and Spanish with English subtitles
    - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, TRT 80:00 (Box 7)
    - DVD master, TRT 80:00 (Box 8)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - A Love Supreme (2001)
    Directed by: Nilesh Patel
    Produced by: Nilesh Patel
    Country: United Kingdom
    Award won: Full Frame Jury Award for Best Short
    TRT: 10:00
    In this stunning and elegant tribute, Patel pays homage to his aging mother as he captures the beauty and artistry of her life's work: making samosas (the Indian stuffed pastry).
    - Preservation print, 35mm, so., co., reel 1 of 1, 720 ft. (Reel 1)
    - DVD master, TRT 10:00 (Box 4)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - Two Towns of Jasper (2001)
    Directed by: Whitney Dow and Marco Williams
    Produced by: Whitney Dow, Marco Williams, Jennifer Latham and Steven Miller
    Award won: Center for Documentary Studies Filmmaker Award
    TRT: 90:00
    In 1998 in Jasper, Texas, James Byrd, Jr., a black man, was chained to a pick-up truck and dragged to his death by three white men. The town was forever altered, and the nation woke up to the horror of a modern-day lynching. For this film, two film crews, one black and one white, set out to document the aftermath of the murder by following the subsequent trials of the local men charged with the crime. The result is an explicit and troubling portrait of race in America, asking how and why a crime like this could have occurred.
    - 35mm, reel 1 of 5, 1620 ft. (Reel 109)
    - 35mm, reel 2 of 5, 1620 ft. (Reel 110)
    - 35mm, reel 3 of 5, 1620 ft. (Reel 111)
    - 35mm, reel 4 of 5, 1620 ft. (Reel 112)
    - 35mm, reel 5 of 5, 1620 ft. (Reel 113)
    - DVD master, TRT 90:00 (Box 4)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - Escuela (2001)
    Directed by: Hannah Weyer
    Produced by: Hannah Weyer and Selina Lewis Davidson
    Award won: MTV>News:Docs:Prize
    TRT: 53:00
    A verité character study, rich in family detail, on the problem of educating the children of migrant workers, this film focuses on the life of Liliana Luis, a fourteen-year-old entering her first year of high school. Weyer follows her family's movement between their home on the Texas borderlands and the California agricultural fields, which leaves Liliana's social, emotional and academic life constantly in flux.
    - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, TRT 53:00 (Box 2)
    - DVD master, TRT 53:00 (Box 4)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - Festival materials, 2002
    - Program Book, including large photocopy (Box 6, Box 19)
    - Programs and Postcards, 2002 (Box 13)
    - Tote Bags, 2002; 3 tote bags (Box 13)
    - T-Shirts, 2002; 2 shirts (Box 13)
    - Foam core posters, 2002; 2 posters (Box 19)
      Scope and Contents
      One poster for Jazz and Blues films; another with large Full Frame Logo
    - Poster, 2002 (Box 19)
- Full Frame Film Festival, 2003
  - Speedo (2003)
    Directed by: Jesse Moss
    Produced by: Jesse Moss
    Award won: Full Frame Audience Award
    TRT: 78:00
    Simultaneously humorous and distressing, this film follows Speedo, a man who has reduced his life to two favorite pastimes: destroying cars and crashing relationships. As his marriage fizzles and his son rebels, Speedo is obsessed with earning recognition at the demolition derby track. The film is a captivating and disturbing portrait of American culture's self-destructive obsession with automobiles, mobility, and disposability.
    - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, TRT 78:00 (Box 3)
    - DVD master, TRT 78:00 (Box 4)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - The Luckiest Nut in the World (2002)
    Directed by: Emily James
    Produced by: Christopher Hird
    TRT: 25:00
    The film follows an animated American peanut who sings about the difficulties faced by nuts from developing countries. Mr. Peanut takes the viewer through the stories of the cashew, brazil and ground nuts in Mozambique, Bolivia, and Senegal, respectively-all of whom suffer as world trade is liberalized. But it is a different story in the U.S., where the peanut is protected by tariffs and heavily subsidized, and worth over four billion dollars a year to the American economy, making it the luckiest nut in the world.
    - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, TRT 25:00 (Box 1)
    - DVD master, TRT 25:00 (Box 4)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - Flag Wars (2003)
    Directed by: Linda Goode-Bryant
    Produced by: Linda Goode-Bryant and Laura Poitras
    An in-depth look at urban gentrification, this film follows an African American, working-class neighborhood in Columbus, Ohio, facing an influx of white, professional newcomers who are mostly gay and lesbian. Filmed over the course of four years, it considers all sides of the story, including a judge caught in the middle. Tensions erupt over conflicting interests and values, exposing divisions along lines of race, sexual orientation, politics and especially class, as two historically oppressed groups bring out prejudice and insensitivity in each other.
    - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, TRT 86:00 (Box 7)
    - DVD master, TRT 86:00 (Box 4)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - Love and Diane (2002)
    Directed by: Jennifer Dworkin
    Produced by: Jennifer Dworkin
    TRT: 153:00
    Filmed over ten years, this is the story of three generations of a family trying to break a cycle of drug abuse and child neglect, centered on the fraught relationship between Diane and her daughter Love. A victim of the 1980s crack cocaine epidemic when Love was born, Diane lost custody of her six children for many years before reuniting them as teenagers. Eighteen now and a mother herself, Love must reconcile her anger towards her mother, as she struggles to care for her baby Donyaeh and, after he is taken into foster care, regain custody of him. Meanwhile, Diane strives to find her second chance, through therapy and job training programs, while trying to prevent her children from repeating her own mistakes. Through the experiences of this family as they try to improve their situation, the film reveals how the Byzantine social welfare system that aims to help such families can also frustrate and limit them. Ultimately, the emphasis is on a human journey towards love and forgiveness.
    - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam (Part 1/2), TRT 82:00 (Box 10)
    - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam (Part 2/2), TRT 71:00 (Box 10)
    - 35mm, reel 1 of 9, 1530 ft. (Reel 136)
    - 35mm, reel 2 of 9, 1530 ft. (Reel 137)
    - 35mm, reel 3 of 9, 1530 ft. (Reel 138)
    - 35mm, reel 4 of 9, 1530 ft. (Reel 139)
    - 35mm, reel 5 of 9, 1530 ft. (Reel 140)
    - 35mm, reel 6 of 9, 1530 ft. (Reel 141)
    - 35mm, reel 7 of 9, 1530 ft. (Reel 142)
    - 35mm, reel 8 of 9, 1530 ft. (Reel 143)
    - 35mm, reel 9 of 9, 1530 ft. (Reel 144)
    - DVD master, TRT 153:00 (Box 8)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - Onibus 174 (2002)
    English title: Bus 174
    Directed by: Jose Padilha
    Produced by: Marcos Prado
    Country: Brazil
    Award won: The Charles E. Guggenheim Emerging Artist Award
    TRT: 120:00
    This intense film tells the story of the infamous Bus 174 Affair, when on June 14, 2000, a bus mugging in Rio de Janeiro turned into a frenzied hostage ordeal broadcast live on television. Making dramatic use of footage shot that day, Padhila turns the tale into more than just an afternoon of horror, revealing the hostage-taker as a boy forced to live as a street kid after society systematically denied him any kind of social existence.
    In Portuguese with English subtitles
    - 35mm, reel 1 of 7, 1543ft. (Reel 2)
    - 35mm, reel 2 of 7, 1543 ft. (Reel 3)
    - 35mm, reel 3 of 7, 1543 ft. (Reel 4)
    - 35mm, reel 4 of 7, 1543 ft. (Reel 5)
    - 35mm, reel 5 of 7, 1543 ft. (Reel 6)
    - 35mm, reel 6 of 7, 1543 ft. (Reel 7)
    - 35mm, reel 7 of 7, 1543 ft. (Reel 8)
    - DVD master, TRT 120:00 (Box 4)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - Festival materials, 2003
    - Program Books and Newsclippings, 2003 (Box 6, Box 14)
    - Lanyard, 2003 (Box 14)
    - Poster, 2003 (Oversize-folder 1)
    - Tote Bag, 2003 (Box 14)
    - T-Shirts, 2003; 2 shirts (Box 14)
- Full Frame Film Festival, 2004
  - Born Into Brothels (2003)
    Directed by: Ross Kauffman and Zana Briski
    Produced by: Ross Kauffman and Zana Briski
    A tribute to the resiliency of childhood and the power of art, this film is a portrait of several children who live in Calcutta's red light district where their mothers work as prostitutes. Briski gives each child a camera and teaches them how to take pictures, nurturing their powers of observation, while trying to help them escape a grim future. The children eagerly photograph the people and places in their neighborhoods, defying the tear-stained tourist snapshot of the global underbelly.
    In English and Bengali with English subtitles
    - 35mm print, So., co., 1.85:1 FLAT Dolby SRD, reel 1 of 5, 1500 ft. (Reel 9)
    - 35mm print, So., co., 1.85:1 FLAT Dolby SRD, reel 2 of 5, 1500 ft. (Reel 10)
    - 35mm print, So., co., 1.85:1 FLAT Dolby SRD, reel 3 of 5, 1500 ft. (Reel 11)
    - 35mm print, So., co., 1.85:1 FLAT Dolby SRD, reel 4 of 5, 1500 ft. (Reel 12)
    - 35mm print, So., co., 1.85:1 FLAT Dolby SRD, reel 5 of 5, 1500 ft. (Reel 13)
    - DVD master, TRT 80:00 (Box 4)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - Word Wars (2004)
    Directed by: Julian Petrillo and Eric Chaikin
    Produced by: Eric Chaikin
    TRT: 80:30
    Word Wars portrays the cutthroat intellectual competition of the world of professional tournaments in Scrabble, the classic board game. This film documents the ordeals suffered by those dedicated to Scrabble dominance, committing to rigid training regimens in order to compete in as many as eight matches in a single day, triumphing over their own physical and economic setbacks.
    - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, TRT 80:30 (Box 3)
    - DVD master, TRT 80:30 (Box 4)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - A Thousand Words (2003)
    Directed by: Melba Williams
    Produced by: Melba Williams
    Award won: Full Frame Grand Jury Award for Best Short
    TRT: 8:25
    A daughter regrets the words never spoken between her and her father, especially after a stroke limiting his ability to communicate. Rodney Williams served in Vietnam, but was always evasive about his experiences, obscuring his stoic silence with playful humor. But he kept a visual record in Vietnam, carrying both a still camera and an 8mm movie camera with him everywhere; his vivid images still speak to what his words cannot.
    - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, TRT 8:25 (Box 5)
    - DVD master, TRT 8:25 (Box 4)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - Super Size Me (2003)
    Directed by: Morgan Spurlock
    Produced by: Morgan Spurlock
    TRT: 98:00
    Morgan Spurlock challenges himself to eat three meals a day at McDonald's for thirty days, while limiting his physical activity to something near the national average. He is medically monitored throughout. At the outset, 32-year-old Spurlock is in excellent health; after a month, he has gained nearly 25 pounds, raised his cholesterol level to 230, and experienced mood swings, sexual dysfunction, and fat accumulation to his liver. His doctors were surprised at the rate of his deterioration. Critical of fast-food advertising to children, the film provides a sometimes humorous look at American food culture and the obesity crisis.
    - Preservation tape master, HDCam, TRT 100:00 (Box 7)
    - DVD master, TRT 100:00 (Box 8)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - Citizen King (2003)
    Directed by: Orlando Bagwell and W. Noland Walker
    Produced by: Orlando Bagwell and W. Noland Walker
    Award won: Full Frame/Emerging Pictures Audience Award
    TRT: 112:00
    This biographical documentary on Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr., brings a fresh focus on his work in the last five years of his life. Broadening his scope beyond race issues to fight poverty and oppose the Vietnam War, he alienated many of his closest associates. This carefully researched film weaves together archival footage and interviews with his contemporaries to offer new insights into King's moral purpose and commitment to social justice.
    - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, TRT 112:00 (Box 3)
    - DVD master, TRT 112:00 (Box 4)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - A Certain Kind of Death (2003)
    Directed by: Blue Hadaegh and Grover Babcock
    Produced by: Blue Hadaegh and Grover Babcock
    Award won: Charles E. Guggenheim Emerging Artist Award
    TRT: 70:00
    An unflinching examination of what happens to those who die with no next of kin, this film follows the deaths of three such individuals in Los Angeles as their cases are processed by the coroner's office. Beginning with removal of the bodies, through burial and disposal of personal possessions, the steps are graphically depicted, gruesome and unsettling. Civil servants go about these tasks professionally, thoroughly, and respectfully, as they weed through clues in the decedent's papers, assembling sad portraits of people left to die alone.
    - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, TRT 70:00 (Box 10)
    - DVD master, TRT 70:00 (Box 8)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - Festival materials, 2004
    - Program Book (Box 6)
    - Programs, Promotional Materials, and Maps, 2004 (Box 14)
    - Water bottle, 2004 (Box 14)
    - Tote bags and t-shirts, 2004; 2 bags; 2 shirts (Box 14)
    - Poster, 2004 (Box 19)
- Full Frame Film Festival, 2005
  - Shape of the Moon (2004)
    Director: Leonard Retel Helmrich
    Producer: Hetty Naaijkens-Retel Helmrich
    Country: The Netherlands
    TRT: 92:00
    Rumidjah is a 62-year-old widow living in Jakarta, Indonesia, with her grown son Bakti and her 11-year-old granddaughter Tari-a Christian family in the largest Muslim country in the world. The film portrays their everyday life, negotiating with money lenders and fighting a neighborhood fire in a bucket brigade. Rumidjah holds fast to her faith, but makes gracious concessions to the Muslim traditions of her neighbors; Bakti is independent and rebellious, but converts to Islam when he marries a Muslim woman. Creative and improbable camera shots illustrate and comment ironically and metaphorically on their situation. This is the second in a trilogy of films about this family by Helmrich.
    - 35mm print, So., co., 1.85:1 FLAT Dolby SRD, reel 1 of 5, 1656 ft. (Reel 126)
    - 35mm print, So., co., 1.85:1 FLAT Dolby SRD, reel 2 of 5, 1656 ft. (Reel 127)
    - 35mm print, So., co., 1.85:1 FLAT Dolby SRD, reel 3 of 5, 1656 ft. (Reel 128)
    - 35mm print, So., co., 1.85:1 FLAT Dolby SRD, reel 4 of 5, 1656 ft. (Reel 129)
    - 35mm print, So., co., 1.85:1 FLAT Dolby SRD, reel 5 of 5, 1656 ft. (Reel 130)
    - DVD master, TRT 92:00 (Box 8)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - Good Times (2004)
    Directed by: Alessandro Cassigoli and Dalia Castel
    Produced by: Alessandro Cassigoli and Dalia Castel
    Country: Italy
    TRT: 31:00
    Abu Dis is a small Palestinian village, divided in two by a wall built by the Israeli government. The film follows the villagers' lives from before the wall, through the construction of first a temporary, then a final wall. Moving in colliding microcosms, the inhabitants of the village and the Israeli soldiers protecting the border create an absurd routine of mutual respect and resentment.
    In Arabic, English and Hebrew, with English subtitles
    - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, TRT 31:00 (Box 2)
    - DVD master, TRT 31:00 (Box 4)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - The Self-Made Man (2004)
    Director: Susan Stern
    Producer: Susan Stern
    TRT: 58:00
    The right-to-die debate goes West in this riveting portrait of a man and his family grappling with a darker side of rugged individualism. On Independence Day, Bob Stern finds out he is seriously ill-possibly dying. Bob decides to cheat that fate and take his own life. His family tries to stop him. But first, they set up a video camera. Part King Lear, part Western, the film offers an intimate exploration of nuclear family dynamics and a complex portrait of what is arguably a specifically American brand of hubris.
    - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, TRT 58:00 (Box 2)
    - DVD master, TRT 58:00 (Box 4)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - The Education of Shelby Knox (2005)
    Directors: Marion Lipschutz and Rose Rosenblatt
    Producer: Marion Lipschutz
    Awards won: Emerging Pictures Audience Award and the Women in Leadership Award
    TRT: 76:00
    This film takes us through three tumultuous years in the life of an idealistic high school student in Lubbock, Texas. We watch as she comes to question and resist the religious and political conservatism inculcated by her concerned, loving parents and overweening pastor, and fights for sex-education in her abstinence-only high school curriculum and the rights of a gay-straight alliance against complacent peers and the entrenched power of co-opting politicians.
    - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, TRT 76:00 (Box 2)
    - DVD master, TRT 76:00 (Box 4)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - Our Brand Is Crisis (2005)
    Director: Rachel Boynton
    Producer: Rachel Boynton
    Award won: Charles E. Guggenheim Emergin Artist Award
    TRT: 85:00
    To mold the strategy for his 2002 campaign for the presidency of Bolivia, Gonzalo "Goni" Sánchez de Lozada hired an American consulting firm. Stanley Greenburg, James Carville and Robert Shrum applied lessons from U.S. elections on branding and marketing to lead Goni to a narrow victory. Fourteen months later, he was forced to resign during the 2003 Bolivian gas protests over privatization, in which 100 people died. With remarkable access to backroom conversations, Boynton captures the campaign process as well as the key players' later reflections on the political effects and ethical implications of their work.
    - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, TRT 85:00 (Box 7)
    - DVD master, TRT 76:00 (Box 8)
    - DVD use copy (Box 11)
  - Rang-i 'ishq (The Color of Love) (2004)
    English title: The Color of Love
    Director: Maryam Keshavarz
    Producer: Maryam Keshavarz
    Country: Iran
    Award won: Full Frame Spectrum Award
    TRT: 69:00
    Set against the dramatic backdrop of the Ashura holy days, this film explores the meaning of love among a cross section of Teheran's middle class. Caught between ancient traditions and a 21st-century perspective informed by satellite TV and the Internet, they struggle to find romance amid the strict moral codes of their country. Iranians young and old, married and single, speak candidly about love, marriage, and sex, revealing what it's like to seek and find love in modern Iran.
    In Persian/Farsi, with English subtitles
    - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, TRT 69:00 (Box 2)
    - DVD master, TRT 69:00 (Box 4)
    - DVD use copy (Box 12, Video-disc data_value_missing_b95f4eddca406bc13d5ec1d18008078d)
  - Wetback: The Undocumented Documentary (2004)
    Director: Arturo Perez Torres
    Producer: Heather Haynes
    Country: Canada